Finding Aid for St. Paul African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church, Detroit, Mich., Records 1957-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Paul African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church, Detroit, Mich., Records 1957-2002
St. Paul African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church (Detroit, Mich.)
7 linear feet
Correspondence, administrative files, Sunday bulletins, and topical files relating to the activities of the church and its pastors, most notably William Hilliard and William C. Ardrey.
89499; Ba 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group (donor no. 7621 ) came to the library, November 1988. A subsequent addition was received in 2003.
The record group is open for research.
St. Paul African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church, "the church of the friendly welcome," in Detroit, Michigan, was founded by Bishop George L. Blackwell in 1911. St. Paul's growth and strength depended on two factors: securing buildings in which the faithful could worship and the inspiring leadership of dynamic pastors. Over the course of time, the congregation of St Paul has met in various venues ranging from the original church on Catherine Street, to the old Vaudette Theatre on Gratiot, to a new church on Catherine, to a facility at Palmer and Beaubien, to the present building at Dexter and Lawrence. Throughout its history St. Paul has benefited from the careful guidance of its pastors, men sensitive to the spiritual needs of the congregation and to the economic difficulties of maintaining a church.
The first pastor of St. Paul A. M. E. Zion was Rev. James A. Terry who handled the challenge resulting from the burning down of the original Catherine Street building in 1916. Terry left the congregation in the competent hands of Rev. L. Thomas Conquest in 1918. For a time Conquest presided over services in the Vaudette Theatre, until the congregation was able to purchase a new church on Catherine. The dynamic Rev. P. R. Flack took the reins as pastor in 1922 and shepherded the congregation through the difficult times of the depression. Despite economic hardships, Flack was able to transplant the church to the west side facility at Palmer and Beaubien. Rev. Lott P. Powell returned to St. Paul in 1941 to serve as pastor. Powell developed organizational structures within the church which endure to the present. He served with distinction until his passing in 1946.
In 1947 the Rev. William A. Hilliard became pastor. He was well suited to the task, building the membership to a number which outgrew the Palmer and Beaubien edifice. This precipitated the moving of the church to its present location at Dexter and Lawrence. In the course of the move, the congregation divided into two Zion Churches. The group which stayed behind is known as the Metropolitan Church and was led by Rev. Stephen P. Spotswood. Hilliard fulfilled his pastoral tasks so well that he was elevated to the position of Bishop in the A. M. E. Zion Church in 1960.
In June 1960 Dr. William C. Ardrey became the pastor of St. Paul and ably led the sixth largest congregation in Detroit. Ardrey stepped up the level of community involvement begun by Hilliard, opening the doors of St. Paul for local groups' meetings and personally taking action to improve the neighborhood and city. Ardrey's involvement in the local NAACP, service on the Detroit Public Library board, and mediation in the 1983 teachers' strike evidence his social commitment. The acme of his activism, securing federal funds for a housing project for the elderly and low income families, was cast into shadow as the loans came due before the building could be occupied. Rev. William M. White succeeded Ardrey in 1989.
The records of St. Paul A.M.E. Zion Church have been arranged into five series: Administrative, Topical Files, Correspondence, Photographs, and Sunday Bulletins.
Subjects:
African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church--Michigan--Detroit.; African American churches--Michigan--Detroit.; African Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; St. Paul African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church--Michigan--Detroit.; African American churches--Michigan--Detroit.; African Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; St. Paul African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Contributors:
Ardrey, William C.; Hilliard, William Alexander, 1904-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series covers the period 1957-2002 and is the largest portion of the record group. In addition to the church's quarterly conference minutes, this series also documents its activities within the Michigan Conference and within the General or national conference. Under "Financial" are formal, detailed, annual and quarterly reports containing information about nearly all of the church's expenditures and receipts. It should be noted that financial information about the status of various church projects can be found scattered throughout this series. Under "Pastors," the researcher will find information about pastors Hilliard and Ardrey. Although most of these files relate to the activities of Pastor Ardrey, files of Bishop Hilliard have been separately donated to the library and may be found cataloged under his name. The Ardrey files reflect his concern for his community and his desire to improve the educational system. Materials from many of the committees that he worked on - including the Property Release Option program, Citizens for Millage, and the Task Force on School/Community Relations - are found in this portion of the Administrative series.
  St. Paul A.M.E. Zion Church was also involved in a housing project, 1966-1978, and records from this undertaking are found under the heading "St. Paul Housing Corporation." Designed to be an affordable housing alternative for the elderly and low income families, this project was financed by a federal government loan. Unfortunately, the project never materialized as anticipated because the loan came due before construction was completed.
  The Administration series also includes materials on some of the organizations within the church, such as its clubs, the board of stewards and the board of trustees. The researcher will get a sense of the church's membership by examining the funeral notices, many of which contain brief summaries of the lives of deceased members. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by name of member. There are also funeral notices scattered among the most recent Sunday Bulletins.
  - General (Box 1)
  - Activities
    - General (Box 1)
    - Men's Day (Box 1)
      (membership rosters, breakdown of groups, liquidation of mortgage)
    - St. Paul Day 1978-1980, 1983 (Box 1)
      (includes rosters, divisions of groups, prize information)
    - Summer Youth Program (Box 1)
      (includes license and agreement with the City of Detroit)
    - Woman's Day Committee 1962 (Box 1)
      (includes roster and minutes of meetings)
  - Adult Sunday School Department (Box 1)
    (includes class rosters, reports, minutes from meetings, goals and purpose of department)
  - Anniversary publications and related (Box 1)
    (various dates; mostly membership rosters)
  - Annual members meeting 1960-2002 (Box 1)
    (scattered dates; include minutes, detailed financial reports)
  - Ardrey, William C. (Box 1)
    (see Pastors)
  - Articles of Incorporation (Box 1)
  - Assistant Pastor 1961-1963 (office budget and activities) (Box 1)
  - Baptism records (Box 1)
  - Chevrolet (bill of sale) 1960 (Box 1)
  - Christian Education Department 1962 (Box 1)
    (includes financial reports and minutes of meetings)
  - Clubs and other church organizations
    - General (Box 1)
      (financial contributions to church, rosters, development plans, programs)
    - Calendar Club (rosters of birthdays) (Box 1)
    - Federation of Clubs (Box 1)
      (financial information on many of the clubs within the church)
    - Inspirational Usher Board 1977 (Box 1)
    - Zion Chorus minute books 1968-1969, 1972-1974, 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Communion: record of number of communicants 1960-1989 (Box 1)
  - Conferences
    - Quarterly Conferences minute books 1959-1990, 3 volumes (Box 1)
    - Michigan Conference
      - 1957-2000 (Box 2)
        (annual meeting of A.M.E. Zion churches; includes agendas, reports, financial reports prepared for conference, voting results; some years missing)
      - Schedules and directories (Box 2)
    - General Conference
      - 1968 (Box 2)
      - 1982, 2 folders (Box 2)
        (preparation of St. Paul as host of national conference, including correspondence, program rosters)
  - Duplex Envelope Company (unpaid bill) (Box 2)
  - Financial
    - General (Box 2)
    - Annual reports 1960-1990 (Box 2)
      (information on annual expenditures and receipts for every area of the church; some years missing)
    - Quarterly Conference 1960-1984, 9 folders (Box 2)
      (expenditures and money received by clubs and other church organizations; some years missing)
    - Steward Board bills 1961 (Box 2)
    - Tax exemption and assessment statements (Box 2)
    - Trustee Board (Box 2)
      (monthly cash received, reports, minutes of meetings)
    - Weekly financial reports 1982-1985 (money received), 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Fund raising (Box 2)
    (sales records detailing the selling of subscriptions to Ebony Magazine)
  - Funeral notices, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Hilliard, William (Box 3)
  - Insurance 1962-1972 (Box 3)
    (forms, policies, correspondence; some years missing)
  - Land survey records (Box 3)
  - Litigation
    - Cavell Candy Company vs. St. Paul A.M.E. Zion Church 1962 (Box 3)
    - First Independence National Bank vs. St. Paul Non-Profit Housing Corporation (Box 3)
    - Tugwell vs. St. Paul A.M.E. Zion Church (Box 3)
    - Warthum vs. St. Paul A.M.E. Zion Church (Box 3)
  - Marriage record book (Box 3)
  - Membership: new members record book 1959-1988 (Box 3)
  - Membership Rosters 1962-1964 (Box 3)
  - Membership Training Course (Box 3)
    (names of people who have completed it)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Mortgage records (Box 3)
  - Music 1960, 1975 (Box 3)
    (includes material regarding resignation of music director)
  - Non-Profit paper (Box 3)
  - Pastors
    - Ardrey, William C.
      - Ad Hoc Committee of Citizens Concerned with Equal Educational Opportunity 1966 (Box 3)
      - Black Leaders' Seminar (summary statement from seminar) 1984 (Box 3)
      - Black United Fund 1984 (Box 3)
      - Christian Communication Council of Metro Detroit Churches (rosters, by-laws) 1979-1984 (Box 3)
      - Christian education 1980, 1985 (Box 3)
        (includes proceedings from 1985 convention)
      - Citizens for Millage (Box 3)
        (Ardrey was co-chairman)
      - Civil rights (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, personal 1960-1969 (Box 3)
      - Department of Home Missions 1980 (Box 3)
      - Detroit area A.M.E. Zion Ministers minutes 1979 (Box 3)
      - Legal Aid and Defender Association of Detroit (Box 3)
        (Ardrey was director)
      - Livingston College 1961 (Box 3)
      - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People 1971 (Box 3)
        (re: preparation for Black Charities Football Classics)
      - Personal (insurance, mortgage) 1957-1977 (Box 3)
      - Publications (commemorative) (Box 3)
      - Property Release Option Program 1978-1979 (Box 3)
        (project to renovate abandoned HUD homes)
      - School Community Relations Task Force (Box 3)
        (plans for improving school-community relations)
      - Sermon notes undated (Box 3)
        (no author indicated, though Ardrey is probably the author)
      - Southern Christian Leadership Conference (Box 3)
    - Hilliard, William (Box 3)
  - Pension Plan, proposed 1977 (Box 3)
  - Publications and programs (miscellaneous) (Box 3)
  - Publications: newsletter, St. Paul Epistle (Box 3)
  - St. Paul A.M.E. Zion Credit Union 1960-1984 (Box 3)
    (mostly financial and statistical reports)
  - St. Paul's Day Care Center (financial information) (Box 3)
  - St. Paul Housing Corporation
    - General 1966-1978, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - Blueprints and undated material (Box 4)
  - Stewards of St. Paul (rosters and resolutions) (Box 4)
  - Trustee Board (Box 4)
    (includes minutes, financial reports. agendas)
  - Westlawn Cemetery Association 1978 (Box 4)
    (re: complaint about maintenance of grounds)
  - "Youth Gazette" newsletter 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    (scattered dates)
  - "Zion's Historical Catechism" (Box 4)
    (includes religious origins of A.M.E. Zion Church)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series, covering the period 1961-1985, contains material which the church collected reflecting its concerns in areas outside of its day-to-day functions. Here there are materials relating to the national and regional organizations of the A.M.E. Zion Churches, various interfaith Detroit area religious organizations, Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, and several community organizations and projects, such as the Detroit Department of Health's Summer Feeding Program for Children, Operation PUSH, and the Urban Alliance.
  - Affirmative action activities 1961-1962 (Box 4)
    (re: bread companies' hiring practices)
  - African campaign 1962 (Box 4)
    (correspondence from the national organization)
  - Allegheny Conference of A.M.E. Zion Church souvenir program 1962 (Box 4)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity 1961 (Box 4)
  - A.M.E. Zion Church (mailings from national organization) (Box 4)
  - A.M.E. Zion Ministerial Alliance (by-laws) (Box 4)
  - Black community leaders (reports about) 1978 (Box 4)
  - Blackwell Temple 1961 (Box 4)
    (re: false premises and unfair dealing complaint)
  - Block Club (Box 4)
  - Clippings (Box 4)
  - Detroit Council of Churches (Box 4)
  - Equal Education Opportunity (Ad Hoc Committee) 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - General (Box 4)
  - Interfaith Action Council (Box 4)
    (established in response to Detroit riots; includes organizational history, 1967-1968)
  - Interfaith Housing Incorporated 1968-1970 (Box 4)
    (re: low income housing; mostly minutes)
  - Michigan Council of Churches (Box 4)
  - Minister's and Laymen's Association (minutes) 1969 (Box 4)
  - National Christian Youth Council 1983 (Box 4)
    (reports by two church members who participated)
  - Neighborhood Services Department, Program Participant Commodity Food Distribution 1983 (Box 4)
  - Operation PUSH 1975 (Box 4)
  - Summer Feeding Program for Children 1978 (Box 4)
    (administered by the Detroit Department of Health)
  - Trial Committee 1960 (Box 4)
    (re: maladministration of Rev. Hiram Crawford)
  - Urban Alliance Incorporated (by-laws) 1969 (Box 4)
  - Wayne State University 1985 (Box 4)
    (re: alleged discrimination against a Black dean)
  - Wedding ceremony (Box 4)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence spans the years 1955-1985 and contains both incoming and outgoing correspondence, mostly of the Rev. William Ardrey. Even though the files cover a 20-year period, the correspondence is often scattered with no files extant for some years.
  - Undated (Box 4)
  - 1955-1985, 10 folders (Box 4)
    (some years missing; scattered dates throughout the files)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series contains a scattering of portraits of church pastors and of church groups.
  - Portraits of church groups and clergy (Box 4)
- Sunday Bulletins
  Sunday Bulletins is the last series in the record group. The bulletins, dating from 1972 to the present, are weekly reports of the activities of the church. Included are tallies of what individual members of the church have contributed. Although fairly complete, there are missing issues of the bulletin.
  - 1972-1987, 19 folders (Box 5)
  - 1987-2002 (Box 6)
    (not organized; include programs for funerals)
  - 1987-2002 (Box 7)
    (continued)